[{"question":"<p><strong>200 cm<sup>3<\/sup> of air was passed over heated copper in a syringe several times to produce copper (II)&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>oxide. When cooled, the final volume of air recorded was 158 cm<sup>3<\/sup>. Estimate the percentage of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>oxygen in the air.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["31%","27%","21%","19%"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A mixture of sand, ammonium chloride and sodium chloride is best separated by __&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Sublimation followed by addition of water and filtration","Sublimation followed by addition of water and evaporation","Addition of water followed by filtration and sublimation","Addition of water followed by crystallization and sublimation"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>CH<sub>4<\/sub> has this geometry:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Trigonal","Planar","Tetrahedral","Octahedral"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Chlorine, consisting of two isotopes of mass numbers 35 and 37, has an atomic mass of 35.5.&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>The relative abundance of the isotope of mass number 37 is ___<\/strong><\/p>","options":["20","25","50","75"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these atomic shells is the most stable&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["M","N","K","L"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Sieving is a technique used to separate mixtures containing 20% oxygen by volume. Which of&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>the reactants was in excess?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Carbon (II) oxide","Oxygen","Carbon (IV) oxide","Nitrogen"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The ideal gas equation is ___&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["P=nRT","PR =nVT","PV =gRT","V=kT"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The number of atoms in one mole of a substance is equal to&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The atomic number","The Avogadro\u0092s number","Number of neutrons","Number of electrons"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The number of electrons in the outermost shell of the atom represents its&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Period","Number of shells","Group","Atomic number"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The partial pressure of oxygen in a sample of air is 500 mmHg. If the total Pr pressure 780 mmHg, what is the mole fraction of the oxygen?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.64","5.73","1.56","0.70"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The periodic classification of the elements is an arrangement of the elements in order of their<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Atomic weights","Isotopic weights","Molecular weights","Atomic numbers"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The shapes of CO<sub>2<\/sub>, H<sub>2<\/sub>O and CH<sub>4<\/sub> respectively are&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Bent, linear and tetrahedral","Bent, tetrahedral and linear","Tetrahedral, linear and bent","Linear, bent and tetrahedral"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>This compound exhibits ionic bonding&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["H20","H2","KC1","NH3"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which one of the following changes is physical?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Adding iron filings to aerated water","Adding sodium metal to water","Cooling a solution of iron(II) sulphate to obtain the hydrated salt","Cooling water to obtain ice"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A side effect of soft water is that&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It gives offensive taste","Excess calcium is precipitated","It encourages the growth of bacteria","It attacks lead contained in pipes"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Ammonia is very soluble in water because it is a \/an molecule&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Non-polar","Polar","Reactive","Basic"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Soap lather is an example of a colloid in which a&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Liquid is dispersed in gas","Solid is dispersed in liquid","Gas is dispersed in liquid","Liquid is dispersed in liquid"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The air around a petroleum refinery is most likely to contain.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["CO2, SO3 and N2O","CO2, CO and N2O","SO2, CO and NO2","PH3, H2O and CO2"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The difference between colloids and suspensions is brought out clearly by the fact that while&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>colloids<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Do not scatter light, suspensions do","Can be separated by filtration, suspensions cannot be so separated","Can be separated by a membrane, suspensions cannot","Do not settle out on standing, suspensions do"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The hydrolysis of NH<sub>4<\/sub>Cl salt will give&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Acidic solution","Neutral solution (C) basic solution (D) hot solution","Basic solution","Hot solution"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The pollutants that are likely to be present in an industrial environment are&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["H<sub>2<\/sub>S, SO<sub>2<\/sub> and oxides of nitrogen","NH<sub>3<\/sub>, HCl and CO","CO<sub>2<\/sub>, NH<sub>3<\/sub>, and H<sub>2<\/sub>S","Dust, NO and Cl<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is the basicity of tetraoxosulphate (VI) acid?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2","1","3","4"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following ions is a pollutant in drinking water even in trace amount?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ca2+","Hg2+","Mg2+","Fe2+"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is an example of a double salt&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["NH4Cl","Alum","NaCO3","AlCl3"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>0.16g of methane when burnt increases the temperature of 100g of water by 40<sup>0<\/sup>(C), what is&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>the heat of combustion of methane if the heat capacity of water is 4.2 Jg<sup>-1<\/sup>C<sup>-1<\/sup>? (CH<sub>4<\/sub>=16).<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1,160kJmol<sup>-1 <\/sup>","1,180kJmol<sup>-1 <\/sup>","1,560kJmol<sup>-1 <\/sup>","1,680kJmol<sup>-1 <\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>A charged car battery has ___ energy that can be converted into another energy called ___energy<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Chemical, electrical","Mechanical, chemical","Heat, mechanical","Light, electrical"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>For each oxygen atom in hydrogen peroxide which acts as an oxidant, there is an oxygen atom&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>which acts as a \/an<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Oxidant","Reductant","Oxidizing agent","Catalyst"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given the change of phase: CO<sub>2<\/sub>(g) changes to CO<sub>2<\/sub>(s), the entropy of the system&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Decreases","Increases","Remains the same","Remains mutual"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In which of the following is the entropy change positive?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Reaction between an acid and a base","Addition of concentrated acid to water.","Dissolution of sodium metal in water","Thermal dissociation of ammonium chloride."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these elements is the best reducing agent.&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Pb","Rb","Al","In"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The name of the gas driven off at the negative electrode during the electrolysis of brine is ___<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Hydrogen","Chlorine","Oxygen","Sodium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The oxidation state of P in H<sub>2<\/sub>P<sub>2<\/sub>0<sub>7<\/sub><sup>2-<\/sup> is ___&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["-3","+3","+1","+5"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The oxidation state of S in Ca(HS0<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> is __&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["+2","-2","+4","-4"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The oxidizing agent in the reaction, 3Br<sub>2<\/sub> + 6OH<sup>-<\/sup>&nbsp; = BrO<sub>3<\/sub><sup>-<\/sup> + 5Br<sup>-<\/sup> + 3H<sub>2<\/sub>O is __&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Br<sub>2<\/sub>","OH<sup>-<\/sup>","BrO<sub>3<\/sub><sup>-<\/sup>","e<sup>-<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When heat is absorbed during a chemical reaction, the reaction is said to be ___<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Thermodynamic","Exothermal","Isothermal","Endothermic"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given the reaction at equilibrium: N<sub>2<\/sub>(g) + O<sub>2<\/sub>(g) &harr; 2NO(g) as the concentration of N<sub>2<\/sub>(g)&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>increases, the concentration of O<sub>2<\/sub>(g) will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Decrease","Increase","Remains the same","Vanishes"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>If a reaction is exothermic and there is a great disorder, it means that&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The reaction is in a state of equilibrium","There will be a large increase in free energy","There will be a large decrease in free energy","The reaction is static."],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the chemical reaction of A + B = C +D, more of D is formed&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["If the concentration of A is reduced","If the concentration of B is reduced","If the concentration of C is reduced","If it is continuously removed from the reaction mixture"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In what way is equilibrium constant for the forward reaction related to that of the reverse&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>reaction?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The addition of the two is expected to be one.","The product of two is expected to be one.","The two equilibrium constants are identical.","The product of the two is always greater than one."],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In which reaction will the point of equilibrium shift to the left when the pressure on the system&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>is increased?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["C(s) + O<sub>2<\/sub>(g) ? CO<sub>2<\/sub>(g)","CaCO<sub>3<\/sub>(s) ? CaO(s) + CO<sub>2<\/sub>(g)","2Mg(s) + O<sub>2<\/sub>(g) ? 2MgO(s)","2H<sub>2<\/sub>(g) + O<sub>2<\/sub>(g) ?2H2<sub>2<\/sub>(g)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which is a property of a reaction that has reached equilibrium?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["The amount of products is greater than the amount of reactants.","The amount of products is equal to the amount of reactants.","The rate of the forward reaction is greater than the rate of the reverse reaction.","The rate of the forward reaction is equal to the rate of the reverse reaction."],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following combination of conditions many increase the rate of a chemical&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>reaction.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Decrease in temperature, increase in concentration of the reactant","Increase in temperature, addition of a catalyst, decrease in the surface area of the reactant","Increase in temperature, increase in concentration, addition of a catalyst and increase in the surface area of the reactant","Decrease in temperature, concentration and surface area of the reactants"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Chlorine is produced commercially by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Electrolysis of dilute HCl","Electrolysis of brine","Neutralization of HCl","Heating potassium trioxochlorate (V)"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Liquid oxygen may be produced by condensation of air using this coolant&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Liquid phosphorus","Liquid gas","Liquid paraffin","Liquid nitrogen"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Chlorine is produced commercially by&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Electrolysis of dilute","Electrolysis of brine","Neutralization of HCI","Heating potassium trioxochlorate"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Liquid oxygen may be produced by condensation of air using this coolant&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["liquid phosphorus","liquid gas","liquid paraffin","liquid nitrogen"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of these metals is not an alkali metal&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["K","Cs","Sr","Fr"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>One of theses reactions represents the laboratory preparation of hydrogen.<\/strong><\/p>","options":["C(s) + H2O(l)?CO(g) + H<sub>2<\/sub>(g)","2 Na(s) + 2H<sub>2<\/sub>0(1) ? 2 NaOH(aq) + H<sub>2<\/sub>(g)","Cu(s) + H<sub>2<\/sub>O(l) ? CuO(s) + H<sub>2<\/sub>(g)","Zn(s) + 2HCl(aq) ? ZnCl<sub>2<\/sub>(aq) + H<sub>2<\/sub>(g)"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The formation of ozone by reaction of O<sub>2<\/sub> with atomic oxygen in UV light occurs in&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Upper atmosphere","Inner atmosphere","Strastosphere","Hemisphere"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The halogen which is chiefly produced commercially from sea water is ___&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Fluorine","Chlorine","Bromine","Iodine"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The most stable allotropic form of sulphur at normal conditions is ___&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Monoclinic sulphur","Rhombic  sulphur","Amorphous sulphur","Plastic sulphur"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>The products obtained when the following chemical reaction is completed and balanced&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>are&hellip;HNO<sub>3<\/sub> + Ca(OH)<sub>2<\/sub> &rarr; ______<\/strong><\/p>","options":["CaNO<sub>3<\/sub> + H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Ca(NO3)<sub>2<\/sub> + 2 H<sub>2<\/sub>O","CaO + 2 NO<sub>2<\/sub> + 3H<sub>2<\/sub>O","Ca + 2 NO<sub>2<\/sub> + 2 H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is the role of iron and Aluminium oxide in ammonia production?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Dehydrating agent","Catalytic agent","Oxidizing agent","Bonding agent"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not allotrope of carbon?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Diamond","Graphite","Buck ministerfullerene","None of the above"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which oxide is amphiprotic (amphoteric)?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["MgO","NaO","CaO","ZnO"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Alkanoic acids are weak acids and ionises in solution to give:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["(A) R<sub>+<\/sup> + COOH","RCOO- + H<sup>+<\/sup>","RCOO<sup>+<\/sup> + H-","RCORCO+ + OH- + OH-"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>An excess of ethanol heated with concentrated H<sub>2<\/sub>SO<sub>4<\/sub> at a temperature of 180<sup>o<\/sup>C is dehydrated&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>to give mostly<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ethane","Ethene","Ethanol","Ethoxyethane"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Butene can be distinguished from benzene by reaction with:&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Hydrochloric acid","Bromine water","Potassium sulphate","Sodium hydroxide"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>In the manufacture of soap industrially, brine is used to __________ the acid salt.&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Oxidise","Reduce","Bleach","Precipitate"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Methane gas can be made from carbon (II) oxide gas according to the equation&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>2CO(g) + 2H2(g) &rarr; CH4(g) + CO2(g). Calculate the mass of CO required to produce 8.75 x 1025&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>molecules of CH4? {At masses: C=12.011, H= 1.008, O = 15.999, Avogadro&rsquo;s no: 6.022 x&nbsp;10<sup>23<\/sup>molecules \/mole.}&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["8140g","4070g","1600g","20.35g"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Potasium ethanoate is formed when:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Methanoic acid reacts with KOH","Ethanoic acid reacts with KOH","Methanol reacts with KCO3","Ethanol reacts with CH3COOH"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is the process associated with conversion of vegetable oil to soap?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Esterification","Saponification","Hydrolysis","Acidification"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When ethanal vapour is passed over manganese (II) ethanoate (manganese acetate) catalyst in&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>the presence of air, the product is:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ethanoate","Ethanol","Methanol","Ethanoic acid"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>When KOH is used instead of NaOH in the production of soap, it has the following advantages&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>except it gives:<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Softer soap","Harder soap","Soap with lower melting point","More soluble soap"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p>&nbsp;<\/p>\r\n<p><strong>When palm wine is left exposed to air for a few days, it goes sour. The bacteria in the air&nbsp;<\/strong><strong>oxidises ________ in palm wine to _________<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ethanol, ethanoic acid","Ethanoic acid, ethanol","Ester, ethanoic acid","Ether, ethanol"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not true about benzoic acid? <\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is aromatic in nature","It can be manufactured from methylbenzene","It has molecular formula C6H6COOH","It sublimes readily"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is not true about benzoic acid?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is aromatic in nature","It can be manufactured from methylbenzene","It has molecular formula C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>COOH","It sublimes readily"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of these is not a property of ethanedioic acid?&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["It is a stronger acid than ethanoic acid but weaker than inorganic acids","It is a reducing agent","It is an oxidising agent","It is soluble in cold water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2015"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following gases has a characteristic pungent smell, turns red litmus paper blue and forms dense white fumes with hydrogen chloride gas?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["N<sub>3<\/sub>","N<sub>2<\/sub>O","Cl<sub>2<\/sub>","NH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Commercial bleaching can be carried out using<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Sulphur (IV) oxide and ammonia","Hydrogen sulphide and chlorine","Chlorine and sulphur(iv) oxide","ammonia and chlorine"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Mineral acids are usually added to commercial hydrogen peroxide to&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["oxidize it","decompose it","minimize its decomposition","reduce it to water  and oxygen"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following compounds will burn with a brick-red colour in a non-luminous Bunsen flame?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["LiCl","NaCl","CaCl<sub>2<\/sub>","MgCl<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The purest form of iron which contains only about 0.1% carbon is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["pig iron","wrought iron","cast iron","iron pryrite"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A common characteristic between zinc and the other transition elements is the ability to<\/strong><\/p>","options":["have variable oxidation states","form complex ions","act as a catalyst","form a coloured ions"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Geometric isomerism can exist in&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Hex-3-ene","Hexane","Prop-1-ene","3-methyl but-1-ene"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Isomers of C3HgO are&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["1-propanol and 2-propanol","1-propanol and 1-propanol","2-propanol and 2-propanone","2-propanol and 1-propanal"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Carbonhydrates are large molecules with the molecular formula C<sub>x<\/sub>(H2O)<sub>y<\/sub> in which of the following pairs is x equal to y?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["glucose and starch","maltose and fructose","sucrose and fructose","maltose and starch"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>A compound contains 40.0% C. 6-7% H and 53.3% O. If the molecular mass of the compounds is 180, its molecular formula is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["CH<sub>2<\/sub>O","C<sub>3<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>6<\/sub>O<sub>3<\/sub>","C<sub>6<\/sub>H<sub>12<\/sub>O<sub>6<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The alkyne that will give a white precipitation with silver trioxonitrate (V) is&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["CH<sub>3<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub>  C = C CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub> C = C CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> C = CH","CH<sub>3<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>2<\/sub> C = C CH<sub>2<\/sub> CH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>The oxidation number of boron is NaBH<sub>4<\/sub><\/strong><\/p>","options":["-3","-1","+1","+3"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2011"},{"question":"<p><strong>Presence of NaCl in ice will<\/strong><\/p>","options":["lower the boiling point of NaCl","increase the melting point of NaCl","make NaCl impure","lower the freezing point of ice"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>What are the values of x,y and z in the equation below?<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>xNH<sub>3<\/sub> + yO<sub>3<\/sub> -&gt; zNO + 6H<sub>2<\/sub>O<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2,3,4","4,5,4","6,5,4","2,3,4"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Calculate the volume of CO<sub>2<\/sub> measured at s.t.p produced on heating 250g of potassium hydrogen trioxocarbonate (iv) strongly. (K=39, H=1, C=12, O=16)<\/strong><\/p>","options":["28dm<sup>3<\/sup>","2.8dm<sup>3<\/sup>","5.6dm<sup>3<\/sup>","11.2dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The boiling points of water, ethanol, methyl benzene and butan-2-ol are 373.0k, 351.3k, 383.6k and 372.5k respectively. Which liquid has the highest vapour pressure at 323.0k?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["water","methyl benzene","ethanol","butan-2-ol"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Elements P, Q and R have atomic numbers 9, 16 and 20 respectively. Which of them would gain electron(s) during ionic bonding?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Q and R","P and R","P and Q","P, Q and R"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following has the lowest Ph?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["5cm<sup>3<\/sup>of M\/10 HCl","10cm<sup>3<\/sup>of M\/10HCl","20cm<sup>3<\/sup>of M\/8 HCl","15cm<sup>3<\/sup>of M\/2 HCl"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following is an acid salt?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["(NH<sub>4<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> CO<sub>3<\/sub>","CH COONa","KHSO<sub>4<\/sub>","MgSO<sub>4<\/sub> 7H<sub>2<\/sub>O"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Cr<sub>2<\/sub>O<sup>-2<\/sup><sub>7<\/sub> + 14H + 6I -&gt; 2Cr<sup>3<\/sup> + 3I<sub>2<\/sub> + 7H<sub>2<\/sub>O. The changes in the oxidation number of oxygen in the equation above is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0","1","2","7"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>During the electrolysis of CuSO<sub>4<\/sub> solution using PI electrode, which of the following occurs?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["acidity increase at the cathode","oxygen is liberated at the cathode","PH decrcaft   at the cathode","PH of solution increases"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The solubility of a salt of molar mass 100g at 20<sup>o<\/sup>C is 0.34moldm<sup>-3<\/sup>. If 3.4g of salt dissolved completely in 250cm<sup>3<\/sup> of water at that temperature, the resulting solution is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["a suspension","saturated","unsaturated","supersaturated"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following ions is a pollution in drinking water even in trace quantities?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Ca<sup>2+<\/sup>","Pb<sup>2+<\/sup>","Mg<sup>2+<\/sup>","Fe<sup>2+<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Catalyst is important in chemical industry in that<\/strong><\/p>","options":["it affects the purity of the products","it affects the quantity of the products","it increases the time for reaching equilibrium","all of the above"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Alkonoic acid has molecular mass of&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["propanoic acid","botanic acid","pentatonic acid","but-2-iron acid"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>Ethyne undergoes the following reactions except<\/strong><\/p>","options":["polymerization","addition","substitution","etherification"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2009"},{"question":"<p><strong>The partial pressure of N<sub>2<\/sub> in a container at 50<sup>o<\/sup>C in which there are 0.50mole of N<sub>2<\/sub> and 1.2mole of CO<sub>2<\/sub> at a pressure of 2.00 atmosphere is?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.6atm","0.5atm","0.40atm","1.6atm"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Given that the pH of a solution of KOH is 12, what is the concentration of the OH ions?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["0.01mol\/dm<sup>3<\/sup>","1x10<sup>-12<\/sup>mol\/dm<sup>3<\/sup>","1x10<sup>14<\/sup>mol\/dm<sup>3<\/sup>","1x10<sup>-7<\/sup>mol\/dm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2008"},{"question":"<p><strong>Two immiscible liquids with different boiling points can be separated by<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the use of separating funnel","evaporation","distillation","decantation"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>A mixture of CaCl<sub>2<\/sub> and CaO<sub>3<\/sub>, n water can be separated by&nbsp;&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["evaporation","sublimation","distillation","decantation"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Consider the reaction represented by<\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>xPb(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub> -&gt; 2PbO + yNO<sub>2<\/sub> + zO<sub>2<\/sub><\/strong><\/p>\n<p><strong>What are the values of x,y and z respectively?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2,6,3","1,4,2","2,4,1","2,4,2"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>20cm<sup>3<\/sup> of H<sub>2<\/sub> mixed and separated with 100cm<sup>3<\/sup> of air containing 21%O<sub>2<\/sub>. Calculate the volume of the residual gases at 110<sup>o<\/sup>C<\/strong><\/p>","options":["31cm<sup>3<\/sup>","8.11cm<sup>3<\/sup>","90cm<sup>3<\/sup>","110cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>What is responsible for metallic bonding?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["sharing of electrons between the metal atoms","attraction between the atom nuclei and the cloud of electrons","transfer of electrons from one atom to another","attraction between positive and negative ions"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>25cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 1.5M solution of NaCl are added to 50cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 3M NaCl. The moler concentration of the resulting solution is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["2.5M","3M","2.25M","4.5M"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>A solution of salt formed form HCl and NH<sub>3<\/sub> solution is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["acidic","basic","complex","neutral"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following elements will burn in excess oxygen to form a product that is neutral to litmus?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["carbon","hydrogen","sulphur","sodium"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Pollution of underground water by meta ions is very likely in a soil that has high<\/strong><\/p>","options":["acidity","alkalinity","chloride content","nitrate content"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>For most reversible reactions<\/strong><\/p>","options":["the reaction rate increases with time","the reaction rate decreases with time","the rate stabilizes with time","the rate produces a curve with time"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following compounds will leave a metal and residue when heated?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["Cu(NO<sub>3<\/sub>)<sub>2<\/sub>","AgNO<sub>2<\/sub>","K<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>2<\/sub>","Na<sub>2<\/sub>CO<sub>2<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the polymers contains nitrogen?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["nylon","PVC","polythene","cellulose"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>A red precipitate of copper(I) dicarbide is formed when ammonium solution of copper(I)chloride is introduced into<\/strong><\/p>","options":["CH<sub>2<\/sub> = CH-CH<sub>2<\/sub>-CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>-CH<sub>2<\/sub>-C=CH","CH<sub>3<\/sub>-CH<sub>2<\/sub>-CH<sub>2<\/sub>-CH<sub>3<\/sub>","CH<sub>3<\/sub>-C=C-CH<sub>3<\/sub>"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2007"},{"question":"<p><strong>A mixture of iron and sulphur can be separated in<\/strong><\/p>","options":["steam","dilute hydrochloric  acid","dilure sodium hydroxide","hot water"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Calculate the minimum volume of oxygen that is required for complete combustion of a mixture of 20cm<sup>3<\/sup> of CO and 10cm<sup>3<\/sup> of hydrogen<\/strong><\/p>","options":["5cm<sup>3<\/sup>","10cm<sup>3<\/sup>","15cm<sup>3<\/sup>","20cm<sup>3<\/sup>"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>HNO<sub>3<\/sub>+H<sub>2<\/sub>O -&gt; H<sub>3<\/sub>O<sup>+<\/sup>NO<sub>3<sup>-&nbsp;<\/sup><\/sub>is the<\/strong><\/p>","options":["conjugate acid","acid","conjugate base","base"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>How much NaOH is required to make 250cm<sup>3<\/sup> of 0.1mol\/dm<sup>3<\/sup> solution&nbsp;<\/strong><\/p>","options":["10g","1.0g","0.1g","4g"],"answerIndex":2,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>A current of 0.5A flows for 1930 seconds and deposits 0.325g of metal M. If the charge is +2, the relative molecular masss is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["65","32.5","24","40.9"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Emission of chlorofluorocarbon (CFC) into the atmosphere causes<\/strong><\/p>","options":["global warming","acid rain","depletion of ozone layer","greenhouse effect"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following samples will react fastest with dilute HCl?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["10g of powered CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> at 25<sup>o<\/sup>C","10g of lumps CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> at 25<sup>o<\/sup>C","10g of lumps of CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> at 50<sup>o<\/sup>C","10g of powered CaCO<sub>3<\/sub> at 50<sup>o<\/sup>C"],"answerIndex":4,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>The colour exhibited by copper in a test is<\/strong><\/p>","options":["green","lilac","blue-green","crimson"],"answerIndex":3,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>Which of the following statements is correct?<\/strong><\/p>","options":["chlorine bleaches by oxidation while sulphur (iv) oxide bleaches by reduction","chlorine bleaches by reduction while sulphur (iv) oxide bleaches by oxidation","both of them bleach by oxidation","both of them bleach by reduction"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"},{"question":"<p><strong>2-methyl but-2-ene is an isomer of<\/strong><\/p>","options":["pent-1-ene","2-methylpent-2-ene","hex-3-ene","2-methylprop-1-ene"],"answerIndex":1,"examYear":"2006"}]